Mauricio Vásquez Bernal

Computer Networks Engineer
Research Assistant at Polytechnic University of Turin
Birthdate: August 31, 1991 - Nationality: Colombian
mauriciovasquezbernal@gmail.com - https://mauriciovasquezbernal.github.io

Profile

Young computer network engineer with 3+ years of experience in developing software. I am a proactive team member, very motivated and enthusiast about new life challenges. I am used to work remotely, had done it for about 2 and a half years.

I am one of the main developers of Polycube, an open source framework for developing virtual network functions with eBPF and XDP. I play nicely with open source development, I have contributed to different projects like Linux kernel, BPF Compiler Collection (BCC), Open vSwitch (OVS) and Data Plane Development Kit (DPDK).

Experience

Research Assistant Feb 2016 – Present

Polytechnic University of Turin

Medellin, Colombia (Remote)

- Developing of polycube, an open source framework to build fast and lightweight virtual network functions with eBPF
- Developing of high-performance virtual network functions with eBPF and XDP
- Contributing to open source projects like Linux kernel and BCC

ConsultantFeb 2017 - May 2017Nebbiolo TechnologiesMedellin, Colombia (Remote)

Implementing high performant virtual network functions with eBPF

Consultant Sep 2016 - Jan 2017

Plumgrid (Acquired by VMware) Medellin, Colombia (Remote)

• Developing iovisor-ovn, an eBPF datapath for Open Virtual Networking (OVN)

Research Assistant Jan 2015 - Aug 2016

Polytechnic University of Turin

Turin, Italy

- Developing of a high-performance communication channel for inter-VM communication in Open vSwitch
- Contributing to open source projects like Open vSwitch (OvS) and Dataplane Development Kit (DPDK)
- Participating in the Unify European Project

Education

Master of Science in Computer Engineering	Oct 2013 – Dec 2015
Polytechnic University of Turin	Turin, Italy
Bachelor in Electronic Engineering	Mar 2009 – Sep 2013
University of Antioquia	Medellín, Colombia

Skills

Programming	Excellent knowledge of C, good knowledge C++ and Go, basic knowledge of Java,	
Languages	Python	
Computer Networks	Good knowledge of TCP/IP, SDN and NFV, eBPF and XDP, Wireless and LAN technologies, Routing Protocols (interior and exterior).	
Virtualization	Good knowledge of KVM/QEMU, Open vSwitch, Docker and Linux Containers, and Kubernetes. Basic knowledge of OpenStack	
Software Development	Good knowledge of git and debugging systems, experience on open source development	
Operating Systems	Good knowledge of Linux	
Languages	Spanish Native Speaker, Advanced (C1) English and Italian	

Publications

Creating Complex Network Services with eBPF: Experience and Lessons Learned	HPSR
Miano, Sebastiano; Bertrone, Matteo; Risso, Fulvio; Tumolo, Massimo; Vasquez	Jun 2018
Bernal, Mauricio	Bucarest - Romania
Transparent Optimization of Inter-Virtual Network Function Communication in	CloudNet
Open vSwitch	Oct 2016
Vasquez Bernal, Mauricio; Cerrato, Ivano; Risso, Fulvio; Verbeiren, David	Pisa - Italy
A Transparent Highway for inter-Virtual Network Function Communication with	SIGCOMM
Open vSwitch	Aug 2016
Vasquez Bernal, Mauricio; Cerrato, Ivano; Risso, Fulvio; Verbeiren, David	Florianopolis - Brazil

Projects

Polycube github.com/polycube-network/polycube

Polycube is an open source framework for developing fast and lightweight network functions using eBPF and XDP

IOVisor-ovn github.com/iovisor/iovisor-ovn

IOVisor-ovn is an eBPF based datapath for the Open Virtual Networking project. It provides a virtual networking solution for virtual machines in environments like Open Stack.

Squadra Corse Polito facebook.com/pg/SCPolito

Squadra Corse is a student racing team from Polytechnic University of Turin. Each year the team design, build and test an electric car to compete against teams from other universities all around the world.

I was in charge of developing the telemetry and datalogging systems.

Personal Interests

Besides job-related things my major hobby is the cycling, I ride both mountain and road disciplines. In the
last years I have been training hard and participating in different races here in Colombia.